Ted Berrigan Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Ted Berrigan Papers.
undated, 1962-1983.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Berrigan, Edmund Joseph Michael.
2.5 linear feet.
Ted Berrigan, American poet, was born Edmund Joseph Michael Berrigan in Providence, Rhode Island. Berrigan's recognition as a poet came in 1964 with the publication of The Sonnets, for which he received the Poetry Foundation Award. Berrigan died in 1983.
MSS19970020
Biography
Ted Berrigan, American poet, was born Edmund Joseph Michael Berrigan in Providence, Rhode Island. He received a B.A. in 1959 and an M.A. in 1962 from the University of Tulsa. Berrigan was the editor of C magazine and press. In 1966-1967 he taught in the poetry workshop at the St. Mark's Art Project. He was associated with the second generation of the New York School and married to Alice Notley.
Berrigan's recognition as a poet came in 1964 with the publication of The Sonnets, for which he received the Poetry Foundation Award. Berrigan often collaborated with other poets; Ron Padgett, Dick Gallup, Anselm Hollo, Anne Waldman, and Tom Clark, for example.
Berrigan died in 1983.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of correspondence and birthday greetings sent to Berrigan from poets associated with the second generation of The New York School. The letters date from 1962-1983. Anselm Hollo's nineteen letters (1969-1981) reveal the two poets' close collaboration.
Printed works contains poetry sent to Berrigan. Of particular note is Ann Waldman's notebook, “Freaked Out”.
Series III focuses on Lita Hoineck's interview with Berrigan. Her analysis of Berrigan's poetic style is included in Telephone 14, which also contains Berrigan's “Sonnet III”, as well as portions of “Many Happy Returns” and “In the Early Morning Rain”. The manuscript of “The Pursuit of Love” is located in this series.
Two interview transcripts are located in Series IV. Berrigan was interviewed by Charles Ingham in 1978 and by Tom Savage in 1980.
This collection originally included the papers of Berrigan's wife, Alice Notley. The collections were separated in 1997 as a result of a later addition to the collection.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of literary materials, particularly those of the Beat Generation and students of Charles Olson. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
Alice Smith Haynes ed. Donald J. Greiner. “Ted Berrigan,” in American Poets since World War II, part I, Dictionary of Literary Biography, vol. 5 Detroit: Gale Research, 1980 59-61.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Document Types:
Greeting cards.[Notes.]; Correspondence.; Publications.; Interviews.; Transcriptions.; Posters
Occupations:
Poet.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased from Granary Books in 1992.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Correspondence, undated, 1962-1983
  - A - F, 1966-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - G - L, 1964-1981 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - M - R, 1962-1982 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - S - Z, 1968-1982 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified, 1964-1982 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Birthday Greetings, 1978-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Postcards, 1963-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
- Series II: Printed Works, undated, 1969-1982
  - Poetry to Berrigan, 1972-1982 (Box OS,1:, Folder 10)
  - MS notebook from Waldman, undated (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - “Freaked Out”, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
- Series III: Writings, 1978, 1980
  - Telephone 14, 1978 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - “The pursuit of Love: A Reader's Guide to Anselm Hollo”, 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Interviews, 1978, 1980
  - Berrigan/Ingham, 1978 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Berrigan/Savage, 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 16)